Finding Aid for Sault Sainte Marie collection, ca. 1802-1930
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sault Sainte Marie collection circa 1802-1930
Bayliss Public Library (Sault Sainte Marie, Mich.)
89182 Bz Microcopy
Records, 1802-1884, of the American Fur Company at Mackinac Island; records of the collector of customs; records concerning history of Mackinac Island, Sault Ste. Marie, Chippewa County, and Mackinac County, including marriage records for Chippewa County, 1824-1870, minutes of Chippewa County Automobile Association, 1917-1930, and miscellaneous personal diaries.
19 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was made available for microfilming by the Bayliss Public Library.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The original materials comprising the Sault Ste. Marie collection are held by the Bayliss Public Library in Saulte Ste. Marie, Michigan.
The Bayliss Public Library is repository of primary materials relating to the history of the Upper Peninsula and the upper Lower Peninsula of Michigan.
The strength of the Sault Ste. Marie collection is the records of the American Fur Company at Port Mackinac. These records date as early as 1802 and include shipping documents from the Sault Ste. Marie area and nearby ports from 1802 to 1884. Among these documents are shipping manifests, clearance documents, bills of sale, enrolment bonds, Treasury Department circulars to custom collectors at the Port of Sault Ste. Marie and nearby ports, and personal and business correspondence.
Other portions of the collection are files maintained by Myron W. Scranton. Scranton was a son-law and business partner of Peter B. Barbeau.
Subjects:
American Fur Company.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan--Chippewa County.; Chippewa County (Mich.); Fur trade--Michigan.; Mackinac County (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Chippewa County.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- American Fur Company
  - Port Mackinac papers 1802-1815 (Reel 1)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1815-1818 (Reel 2)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1818-1830 (Reel 3)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1831-1834 (Reel 4)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1835-1839 (Reel 5)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1841-1852 include P.B. Barbeau Maritime papers, 1841-1844 (Reel 5)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1841-1852 (cont.) (Reel 6)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1853-1855 include P.B. Barbeau Maritime papers, 1853 (Reel 6)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1853-1855 (cont.) (Reel 7)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1853-1855 (cont.) (Reel 8)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1856-1861 include P.B. Barbeau Maritime papers, 1856 (Reel 8)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1856-1861 (cont.) (Reel 9)
  - Port Mackinac papers 1863-1884 (Reel 9)
  - Port Mackinac Manifests 1807-1838 (Reel 10)
- Myron W. Scranton papers
  - Correspondence 1853, 1865-1867 (Reel 10)
  - Correspondence 1853, 1865-1867 (Reel 11)
    (continued)
  - Correspondence 1868-1871 (Reel 11)
  - Correspondence 1868-1871 (cont.) (Reel 12)
  - Correspondence 1872-1873 (Reel 12)
  - Correspondence 1872-1873 (cont.) (Reel 13)
  - Correspondence 1874-1879 (Reel 13)
  - Correspondence 1874-1917 (Reel 14)
- Miscellaneous other papers and records
  - Collector of Customs
    - Edward Biddle papers (Reel 15)
    - Guy H. Carleton papers (Reel 15)
  - Mackinac Island Collector of Customs 1789-1873 (Reel 15)
  - Guy H. Carlton papers 1846-1924 (Reel 15)
  - U.S. General Land Office Land Grants, etc. 1832-1919 (Reel 15)
  - Miscellaneous small collections and single items 1804-1940 (Reel 15)
  - Miscellaneous small collections and single items 1804-1940 (Reel 16)
  - Essays and sketches on the history and biography of Sault Ste. Marie, typewritten (Reel 16)
  - Achille Frenchett's Account Book 1846 (Reel 16)
  - Diaries, Journals, 1824-1930; include Chippewa County marriages, 1824-1870 (DAR) (Reel 16)
  - County of Chippewa Treasurer's records (Reel 16)
  - P.H. Agarr diary circa 1862 (Reel 16)
  - Minutes of Chippewa County Automobile Association 1917-1930 (Reel 16)
  - Miscellaneous journals, letter press, registers 1808-1866 (Reel 17)
  - Copies of letters written to American Fur Company 1835-1837 (Reel 17)
  - Annuity List for Indians of Michigan 1846 (Reel 17)
  - P.S. Church diaries, 1847, 1850-1852, 1852-1854 (Reel 17)
  - P. Munson Church diary, 1863-1866 (Reel 17)
  - Volume containing copies of indentures, land sales, etc.; and list of people employed in fur trade (names of men, names of employers, and place of wintering) (Reel 17)
  - Sketches accompanying report of coast survey for 1851 (Reel 17)
  - Maps, Broadsides (Reel 17)
  - Pamphlets, Reports, Addresses, and Miscellaneous (Reel 17)
  - Pamphlets, Reports, Addresses, and Miscellaneous (cont.) (Reel 18)
  - Essay on the St. Mary's Canal undated (Reel 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 18)
  - Record book of George A. Ogle Company of Chicago (publishers of atlases, etc.) (Reel 19)